<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Isomorphic</title><link>https://isomorphic.group/</link><description>Recent content on Isomorphic</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://isomorphic.group/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>About</title><link>https://isomorphic.group/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://isomorphic.group/about/</guid><description>Hi there! I&amp;rsquo;m Dan.
I&amp;rsquo;ve always liked to write. I picked up a journaling habit a few years ago, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been regularly recording my ruminations ever since. Peoples' minds work through lots of interesting thoughts and problems throughout their lives. Most go unrecorded, and I think that&amp;rsquo;s a tragedy.
I&amp;rsquo;m interested in lots of things&amp;ndash;mathematics, computer science, philosophy, music, and art, to name the big ones. I enjoy writing about these subjects in isolation, but I especially enjoy writing about the strange, surprising, and often beautiful ways in which they interact or translate to one another (isomorphisms, of sorts).</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hi there! I&rsquo;m Dan.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve always liked to write. I picked up a journaling habit a few years ago,
and I&rsquo;ve been regularly recording my ruminations ever since. Peoples'
minds work through lots of interesting thoughts and problems throughout their
lives. Most go unrecorded, and I think that&rsquo;s a tragedy.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m interested in lots of things&ndash;mathematics, computer science, philosophy, music, and art, to name the big ones. I enjoy writing about these subjects in isolation, but I especially enjoy writing about the strange, surprising, and often beautiful ways in which they interact or
translate to one another (isomorphisms, of sorts).</p>
<p>Outside of these interests, I enjoy mountaineering, skiing, and botany. I&rsquo;m slowly working my way
through the Colorado 14ers, and my collection of carnivorous plants continues to grow! I currently work at Jane Street Capital and am based out of New York City.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>